Guide to the Alexander Pope Collection
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Alexander Pope collection
1713-1855
GEN MSS 270
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
1.2
(2 boxes)
Contains letters from Pope to various people, including John Conduitt, Robert Craggs Nugent, and Jonathan Richardson; a holograph draft of Pope's translation of the first 48 lines of Book 8 of Homer's "Iliad"; a holograph inscription for Jonathan Swift's grandfather's tomb (with holograph notes by Swift); and an album (formerly owned by John Murray) that contains material by and about Pope.
Pope, Alexander, 1688-1744
Homer ( Iliad, Book 8, English)
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Ongoing collection of documents acquired by gift and purchase from various sources. Type of accession (gift or purchase) and date of acquisition is noted in the box-and-folder list. For further information, consult the appropriate curator.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
This finding aid encompasses accessions of single manuscripts and small groups of manuscripts and other papers, by or pertaining to Alexander Pope, which the library has chosen to group and list as an artificial collection.
Authors, English -- Archives; Conduitt, John, 1688-1737; Murray, John, 1808-1892; Nugent, Robert Nugent, Earl, 1702-1788; Pope, Alexander, 1688-1744; Richardson, Jonathan, 1665-1745; Swift, Jonathan, 1667-1745
- Letters from Alexander Pope, [1736] Feb 12; Series I
  - ALS to [Allen, First Lord Bathurst?], Twickenham, [1736] Feb 12 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Scope and Contents
    Purchase, 1983.
  - ALS to "My dear Lord" [Bathurst?], Twickenham, [1739?] Aug 9 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Purchase, 1956.
  - ALS to Hugh Bethel, Twickenham, 1737 Feb 11 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Accompanied by five portraits of Pope. Purchase, 1944.
  - ALS to Mr. Bethel, 1744 Mar 26 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Accompanied by an engraving of Pope. Purchase, 1971.
  - ALS to William Borlase, Twickenham, 1740 Mar 9 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Purchase, 1944.
  - ALS to John Brinsden, [1741] Jun 8 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Accompanied by a copy of a letter from Pope to Brinsden, 1741 Nov 6. Gift, 1957.
  - ALS to Samuel Buckley, [1737 Nov 23] (Box 1, Folder 7)
    "From Lord Cornbury's".
  - ALS to John Conduitt, Twickenham, 1727 Nov 10 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    Accompanied by draft of AL to Pope from Conduitt, 1727 Nov 8; two manuscript copies (one in English and signed, the other in French with manuscript corrections) of Conduitt's dedicatory epistle to Queen Caroline that appeared in Sir Isaac Newton's The Chronology of Ancient Kingdoms Amended... (London, 1728); proof sheets, with manuscript corrections, of signatures A and a containing the title-page, dedicatory epistle, table of contents, and advertisement. Purchase, 1943.
  - ALS to [Thomas Dancastle?], 1719 Nov 9 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - ALS to [William Fortescue], [1732/3] Mar 8
    Gift, 1952.
    Related Archival Materials note
    See: [Robert Craggs Nugent, Lord Nugent], Box 1, folder 10
  - 5 ALS to [Robert Craggs Nugent, Lord Nugent], Twickenham, 1740 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    In volume. With printed transcripts, an envelope addressed to Sir George Nugent in an unidentified hand, and an autograph letter from Pope to William Fortescue, with typescript. Gift, 1952.
  - ALS to Jonathan Richardson, Twickenham, [1734] Nov 4 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - ALS to Mr. [Jonathan] Richardson, [ca. 1737] (Box 1, Folder 12)
    Purchase, 1946.
  - AN and address leaf to Richardson (Box 1, Folder 13)
    Purchase, 1966.
  - ALS to G[eorge Augustus] Selwyn, Twickenham, Sep 27 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    Purchase, 1948.
  - ALS to Sir William Trumbull, [1713 Jun 6] (Box 1, Folder 15)
    Page 3 includes an autograph manuscript letter from Charles Jervas to Sir William Trumbull, 1713 Jun 6. Gift, 1964.
- Other, n.d.; Series II
  - Homer, Iliad, Book 8. English translation by Pope, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 16)
    Autograph manuscript of the first 48 lines. Removed from Pope's copy of George Chapman's translation of Homer's Iliad (London, 1611). Gift, 1966.
  - "A Proper reply to a lady, occasioned by her verses addressed to the Imitator of the First Satire of the second Book of Horace, by Mr. Pope" (Box 1, Folder 17)
    Manuscript copy in an unidentifed hand. Purchase, 1919.
  - Inscription for Jonathan Swift's grandfather's tomb (Box 1, Folder 18)
    With additional notes in hand of Jonathan Swift. Purchase, 1958.
  - Address from letter (clipped), n.d. (Box 1, Folder 19)
    Holograph. Gift, 1953.
  - Album, formerly owned by John Murray, containing items either by Pope or related to him, 1717-1855
    Contains: mezzotint of Pope after Godfrey Kneller, 1722; ALS to Sir Godfrey Kneller, 1717/18 Feb 18; crayon drawing of Pope by Jonathan Richardson, n.d.; printed receipt to Robert Packer, Esq., for the subscription copy of Homer's Iliad, signed: "A. Pope"; ALS to Mrs. Howard, [1729 May]; ALS to Mr. Richardson, Cirencester, [1737] Jun 25; Pope's preface to the Works, with many corrections (removed from album and purchased by Professor Tinker before the Library bought album; now Tinker Ms 1668); first copy of manuscript verses by Pope on the Grotto of Twickenham composed entirely of English metals, minerals, marbles, corrected with his own hand, 1740/1 Feb 6; original proof of two pages from Pope's Epistles, pages 69 and 70, with the author's corrections; 2 ALS from John Murray to John Wilson Croker, London, 1854 May 19 and Jun 8; ALS from John Wilson Croker to Mr. Cooke, 1855 Aug 1; leaf from the printed catalogue of the collection of H. B. Ray, newpaper clippings, and envelope addressed to John Murray in an unidentified hand. Purchase, 1939.
    See: Oversize, Box 2, folder 20
- Oversize, 1717-1855
  - Album, formerly owned by John Murray, containing items either by Pope or related to him (in Series II), 1717-1855 (Box 2, Folder 20)